<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" 
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd">

<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Advanced Options</title>
  <section>
    <title>Units</title>
    <para>
      As mentioned above, AMEE includes built-in support for a wide range of unit conversions. Most units 
      are SI by default, but if you want to specify fuel in US gallons instead, you can. Time units can also 
      be changed. Each parameter in a profile item has associated Unit and PerUnit parameters which control 
      these. For instance, if you wanted to use the default units for fuel, you could add a fuel purchase with 
      the following parameter, which would represent a fuel usage of 100 litres per month.
    </para>
    <programlisting>volume=100</programlisting>
    <para>
      If, however, you are measuring in gallons on a weekly basis, you could specify the following parameters:
    </para>
    <programlisting>volume=100&amp;volumeUnit=gal&amp;volumePerUnit=week</programlisting>
    <para>
      All unit conversion calculations are automatically handled by AMEE, giving you the correct results for your application with the minimum of effort.
    </para>      
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Return Units</title>
    <para>
      Similar to input units, the CO2 emission results generated by AMEE have default units of kg/year. If you 
      prefer pounds per week, you can specify some special parameters in your GET requests:
    </para>
    <programlisting>https://stage.amee.com/profiles/7C7D68C2A7CD/home/energy/quantity?returnUnit=lb&amp;returnPerUnit=week</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section id='paging'>
    <title>Paging</title>
	<para>
	    Many resources in AMEE are capable of containing a large number of sub-resources, for instance 
	    profile categories can contain many profile items. Retrieving them all in one request may be prohibitively
	    expensive, so for this reason such resources are paged. Details of how to page through items in AMEE are provided at <xref linkend="paging_reference"/>.
	  </para>
  </section>
</chapter>

