<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" 
"http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd">

<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Basic Concepts</title>
	<section>
		<title>REST</title>
		<para>Representational State Transfer (REST) is a system for creating efficient programmable interfaces with the World Wide Web. When a client uses the AMEE API to request information from an AMEE server, or provide information to it, is based around the transfer of <emphasis>representations</emphasis> of <emphasis>resources</emphasis>. A representation of a resource is typically a document that captures the current or intended state of a resource. Interactions with a RESTful API create, update, read, or delete a resource. Resources in AMEE include profiles, categories, items, and values. Each resource in AMEE is uniquely referenced by a unique identifier, or UID, a 16-digit random string.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Categories</title>
		<para>A category in AMEE is a collection of items representing energy consuming or other activities which share a common way to calculate their associated greenhouse gas emissions. AMEE categories contain, for example, different types of car or train transport, types of fuel or country-specific grid electricity, electrical appliances, and agricultural or industrial processes.</para>
		<para>Categories in version two of the API are organised in a tree-like structure based around the primary parent categories business, home, embodied, metadata, planet and transport. When interacting with AMEE, the full path is used to specify the use of a particular category (e.g. /business/energy/stationaryCombustion).</para>
		<para>Where similar data exists, perhaps from different sources or representative of different geographic contexts, alternative categories are available for the same type of emissions activity.</para>
	</section>	
<section>
	<title>Data Items</title>
	<para>Data items are the fundamental unit of data organisation and emissions calculations in AMEE. Data items are organised into categories and represent distinct types of activity, such as consumption of a particular type of fuel, a short-haul flight, or the use of an electrical appliance.</para>
	<para>Data items contain two types of information: drill down choices are used for uniquely specifying a particular item, and data item values are used to store emissions factors and other information relevant to that item. A data item may be uniquely specified by giving the path of the data category, and the sequence of drill-down choices. Alternatively, it may be referenced by a UID.</para>
	<para>When developing an application that uses AMEE, you will usually only need to work with profile items. However, it is useful to look at data items if you want to understand what the data means, what assumptions lie behind it and what you need to ask your user. In fact, documenting these aspects is the main purpose of AMEE explorer.</para>
</section>
<section><title>Profile Items</title>
<para>When AMEE is invoked to carry out a calculation, this process creates a profile item, following the REST approach. A profile item is always based on a particular data item, and is created with a reference to that data item. A profile item contains information on a particular aspect of usage or ownership which can be stored and used to calculate the associated greenhouse gas emissions. Once a profile item is created in this way, you can retrieve the kg CO2 (or CO2e) value at any time in the future. You can also retrieve the choices and values stored in the profile item - which represent a record of consumption - so you can display this information to your user when they return to the page at some time in the future.</para>
</section>
<section>
	<title>Profiles</title>
	<para> Profile items are collected into a profiles, corresponding as desired to business sections, individuals, or other carbon emitting groups or entities. A profile could represent an individual, an office, an entire company, or whatever you want, really. 
      It's completely up to you how you want to split up your data; you can create as many profiles as you like. Your application design will probably suggest the most appropriate split, but generally speaking, if something is considered a single energy-using entity in your system, it would have a profile to itself.</para>
</section>

</chapter>