<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" 
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd">

<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Performing Calculations</title>
  <para>
    Now that you're authenticated, we can start to store data and perform calculations. The first step in this is to create a profile.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Creating a Profile</title>
    <para>
      A profile could represent an individual, an office, an entire company, or whatever you want, really. 
      It's completely up to you how you want to split up your data; you can create as many profiles as you
      like. Your application design will probably suggest the most appropriate split, but generally speaking,
      if something is considered a single energy-using entity in your system, it would have a profile to itself.
    </para>
    <para>
      Each profile in AMEE is identified by a 16-digit random string (a profile UID), which you will need to 
      store in your application's database alongside any other user details you might have; if the user comes 
      back later on, you will need the profile UID to retrieve their information again. This is because privacy 
      and security of data are of utmost importance; all data stored in AMEE is anonymised, so you cannot retrieve 
      profile data based on personal information.
    </para>
    <para>
      To create a profile, you can send a POST request to https://stage.amee.com/profiles. You need to send the 
      parameter profile=true in the body, as shown in the following XML example (a JSON example is shown in <xref linkend='create_profile_reference'/>):
    </para>
		<section role='tabbed'>
  		<section role='tab'>
  			<title>XML</title>
  			<section role='httprequest'>
  			  <programlisting role='header'>
POST /profiles HTTP/1.1
Accept: application/xml
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded
Authorization: Basic dXNlcm5hbWU6cGFzc3dvcmQ=
          </programlisting>
          <programlisting role='body'>
profile=true
          </programlisting>
        </section>
        <section role='httpresponse'>
          <programlisting role='header'>
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/xml; charset=UTF-8
          </programlisting>
          <programlisting role='xml-body'><xi:include href='samples/xml/post_profiles.xml' parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </section>
  		</section>
  	</section>
  	<para>
      The important part of this response is the uid attribute in the Profile tag, which in this case has the 
      value YLLIKH73BDYS. This is the UID for the newly-created profile, and forms part of the URL for
      subsequent requests that use that profile.
   </para>
   <para>     
     A profile contains a hierarchy of profile categories, which split up the data that you can store into 
     contextual areas, similar to a folder structure on disk. Top-level categories include such broad sections 
     as "Home", "Business", "Transport", and so on. Each category can contain any number of other categories
      and some categories (the lower-level ones normally) can contain profile items. These are a bit like files, 
      and are where you actually store your energy data.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Adding a Profile Item</title>
    <para>
      Once you've selected the category where you want to store your energy data, you will want to create a profile
      item to store that data. To do this, simply POST to the category URL with an appropriate set of parameters, 
      and your data will be stored in a newly-created profile item. For example, to store some energy data in the 
      /transport/defra/fuel category, you would send the following request:
    </para>
		<section role='tabbed'>
		  <section role='tab'>
  			<title>Example</title>
  			<section role='httprequest'>
  			  <programlisting role='header'>
POST /profiles/YLLIKH73BDYS/transport/defra/fuel HTTP/1.1
Accept: application/json, application/xml
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded
Authorization: Basic dXNlcm5hbWU6cGFzc3dvcmQ=
          </programlisting>
          <programlisting role='body'>
dataItemUid=19B311DDF0B1&amp;volume=500&amp;startDate=2011-01-05T00%3A00%3A00%2B00%3A00
          </programlisting>
        </section>
        <section role='httpresponse'>
          <programlisting role='header'>
HTTP/1.1 201 CREATED
Location: https://{server}.amee.com/profiles/4737069901D3/home/energy/quantity/F0638HOIFC1H
Content-Type: text/plain
          </programlisting>
			  </section>
  		</section>
		</section>
		<para>
      If the request is successful, you get back a 201 CREATED response, with the location of the 
      newly-created item. There are a few things to note here, particularly the parameters in the 
      POST request. The first is dataItemUid, which specifies exactly what type of data you wish to 
      store in the category (in this case, the type of fuel). We will come back to this in more 
      detail in a moment. The second is volume, which is a profile item value specific 
      to this category. As each category can store a different type of data, the profile item values 
      are different for each one, and we will go into more detail on how you can find our which ones
      to use in each category later on. However, in this case, the call will store a value of 500 litres 
      per month for this item. Note that you can select the units you wish to use with your POST - 
      see <xref linkend='units' /> for details.
    </para>
    <para>
      There is one other option, which is useful in many cases. If you pass representation=full as an 
      extra parameter in the POST request, you will get back a representation of the newly-created item, 
      rather than just the location. If you want to get back the CO2 value of the data you have just 
      stored, you will want to do this. The XML representation looks just like a GET response:
    </para>
		<section role='tabbed'>
  		<section role='tab'>
  			<title>XML</title>
  			<section role='httprequest'>
  			  <programlisting role='header'>
POST /profiles/YLLIKH73BDYS/transport/defra/fuel HTTP/1.1
Accept: application/xml
Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded
Authorization: Basic dXNlcm5hbWU6cGFzc3dvcmQ=
          </programlisting>
          <programlisting role='body'>
dataItemUid=19B311DDF0B1&amp;volume=500&amp;startDate=2011-01-05T00%3A00%3A00%2B00%3A00
&amp;representation=full
          </programlisting>
        </section>
        <section role='httpresponse'>
          <programlisting role='header'>
HTTP/1.1 201 CREATED
Content-Type: application/xml; charset=UTF-8
          </programlisting>
          <programlisting role='xml-body'><xi:include href='samples/xml/create_profile_item.xml' parse="text"/></programlisting>
        </section>
  		</section>
  	</section>
  	<para>
      Note the ProfileItem tag. It contains all the details of the new item. The item values are 
      representations of the stored parameters from your POST request. In this case, the item value is volume, 
      and the value is 500. Unit and PerUnit show the units for this item value, in this case litres per month.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can store thousands of different types of energy use in AMEE by finding the appropriate category and
      creating the right items. By setting various parameters, you can store different data values at different
      times, or in different units. We will go into some of these options in the following sections, but first, let's 
      find out how to find out what the actual emissions from our calculation are.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Getting Results</title>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Selecting a Data Item</title>
  </section>
</chapter>
