<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" 
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd">

<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Quick Start</title>
  <section>
    <title>Obtaining an API Key</title>
    <para>
      The first step towards using the AMEE platform is to sign up for an access key. You can do this for free
      at <ulink url="http://my.amee.com/signup"/>. Enter your details, and you will be emailed an API key, 
      as well as links to documentation and other relevant resources.
    </para>
    <para>
      This key will give you access to the AMEE stage platform (stage.amee.com). This platform is free for
      you to use while you are developing and testing your client application. However, the data on it is
      regularly wiped, so once you decide your application is ready to go into production, you will need to
      change over to using the AMEE live platform (live.amee.com, here service fees may apply).
    </para>
    <para>
      Throughout the documentation, the examples will use the AMEE stage platform URL.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Authentication</title>
    <para>
      Once you've got your key, you're ready to start talking to the API itself, and the first step is 
      authentication. There are two methods of authenticating with the API; using HTTP Basic, or by 
      creating an authenticated session.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>HTTP Basic</title>
      <para>
        HTTP Basic authentication is extremely simple. You simply provide your username and password with every 
        request, using the standard HTTP format. Most HTTP libraries will support this functionality; as an 
        example, the following code shows this process in Ruby:
      </para>
      <programlisting role='ruby'>
http = Net::HTTP.new @host, 443
http.use_ssl = true
req = Net::HTTP::Get.new @location
req.basic_auth @username, @password
http.request(req)
      </programlisting>
      <para>
        You should only use HTTP Basic authentication if you are connecting to the AMEE API over SSL. (Using
        SSL is recommended, and all examples in this manual use it.)
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Content Types</title>
  </section>
</chapter>