<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" 
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd">

<chapter xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Time Series</title>
  <para>
    Storing a single profile item is useful, but most data changes over time, particularly 
    when we are talking about energy use. AMEE allows you to store time information along 
    with your data, so that you can build up a series of data points over time.
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Naming Profile Items</title>
    <para>
      If you create two profile items with the same data item UID, and which overlap the same 
      time, then the AMEE API will complain as it can't form a sensible time series from the 
      data. However, there are cases in which you might want to do this; energy used by two 
      cars of the same type, for instance. In this case, you can provide a name parameter to 
      identify each series. You can build up multiple histories in the same profile category 
      by using different names for each one. A name is not required, but if you suspect that 
      you will want to store multiple time series alongside each other, it is good practise 
      to specify one.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Start &amp; End Dates</title>
    <para>
      Three parameters are available to control time information, startDate, endDate, and 
      duration. By providing these when you create profile items, you can set the time 
      that the created profile item is valid for. By default, startDate is "now" and 
      endDate is infinitely far in the future. If your data is not time-sensitive, then 
      this will be fine. However, if your data represents usage at a particular time, you 
      can set the values explicitly. The maximum time resolution of the AMEE platform is 1 
      minute. If seconds are specified, they are rounded down. Note that you can't set 
      endDate and duration at the same time.
    </para>
    <para>
      All these parameters are specified in standard ISO-8601 format. For instance, the 
      following would all be valid parameters (when correctly form-encoded):
    </para>
    <programlisting>startDate=2009-08-01T14:30:55Z
endDate=2009-08-02T14:30:55-08:00
duration=PT30S</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Time Series Queries</title>
    <para>
      Once you have built up a time series, you will probably want to retrieve historical 
      data. Above, we saw that profile categories include a list of current profile items. 
      This "present time" behaviour can be modified by providing startDate and endDate query 
      parameters in the GET request. You can request all data between particular dates, 
      or everything that starts after a certain time.
<para>By default, emission values for items are for the
		  whole item, for any items that overlap the query interval at all, not just the part of the item that intersects the query window. To
		  get just the emissions that took place during the query window, set the mode parameter to 'prorata' with your request.</para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Data Item Value History</title>
<para>Some AMEE data categories have time series for emissions factor data. For these categories, the appropriate values are automatically used for calculating the emissions due to a profile item, so that if, for example, the item has start and end date in 1995, the 1995 emissions factor would be used. Furthermore, if the profile item start and end dates overlap multiple values in the data series, AMEE will sort this out automatically, bringing you the correct total emissions by summing across each period where the data differs.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>