<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" 
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY % sgml.features "IGNORE">
<!ENTITY % xml.features "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % dbcent PUBLIC "-//OASIS//ENTITIES DocBook Character Entities V4.5//EN" "/usr/local/Cellar/docbook/5.0/docbook/xml/4.5/dbcentx.mod">
%dbcent;
]>

<section xml:id='data-item-reference' xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
	<title>Data Items</title>
  <para>
    A Data Item represents a single type of energy usage which contributes to CO2 emissions.
    Data Items provide the data required to perform emissions calculations for Profile Items.
  </para>
  <para>
    For example, a particular Data Item could represent an average sized petrol car. 
    You could create a Profile Item associated with this Data Item, which would specify
    that a user has an average sized petrol car. You could set extra parameters in this
    Profile Item to specify information such as that the car is driven 5000 kilometres per year.
  </para>
  <para>
    Each Data Item can have several Data Item Values (distance, for instance).
  </para>
	<section>
		<title>Properties</title>
		<table class='properties'>
			<tr>
				<th>Property</th>
				<th>Description</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>					
				<td>UID</td>
				<td>A 12-letter unique identifier for the data item. See <xref linkend='uid-reference'/> for more information.</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>					
				<td>created</td>
				<td>The time and date on which the item was created.</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>					
				<td>modified</td>
				<td>The time and date on which the item was last modified.</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>					
				<td>name</td>
				<td>A display name for this Data Item. This is not always used and 
				  will default to the UID.</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>					
				<td>path</td>
				<td>The path segment for this Data Item within the URL path. 
				  This is not always used and will default to the UID.</td>
			</tr>
		</table>
	</section>
	<section xml:id='get-data-item-reference'>
		<title>Get Data Item</title>
		<para>
			Fetches a representation of a data item. If query parameters are provided,
			a calculation is performed.
		</para>
		<table class='requestdetails'>
			<tr><td>URL</td><td>https://{server}.amee.com/data/{category_path}/{data_item_uid}</td></tr>
			<tr><td>HTTP Method</td><td>GET</td></tr>
			<tr><td>Response Content-Type</td><td>application/xml or application/json</td></tr>
			<tr><td>Successful Response Code</td><td>200 OK</td></tr>
		</table>
		<section>
		  <title>Optional Parameters</title>
  		<table class='parameters'>
  			<tr>
					<th>Parameter</th>
					<th>Description</th>
  			</tr>
				<tr>
					<td>{valueName}</td>
					<td>Set a Profile Item Value by specifying the name and value. For example, the value 
					  name could be 'distance' supplied with a value of '300'. Multiple name/value pairs
					  can be submitted so long as the named Item Values exist. Names
					  and values are case sensitive.</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>					
					<td>{valueName}Unit</td>
					<td>If a value is set, a unit can also be set. In the distance example above, the 
					  'distanceUnit' parameter could be set to 'km', 'mi', or any other supported distance 
					  unit. All values have default units if none are supplied.</td>
				</tr>
				<tr>					
					<td>{valueName}PerUnit</td>
					<td>If a value is set, a perUnit can also be set, which indicates the timescale over which
					  the value applies. In the distance example above, the 'distancePerUnit' parameter could be
					  set to 'day', 'month', or any other supported time unit. Not all values support perUnits; check 
					  AMEEdiscover for each case. Relevant values have default perUnits if none are supplied.</td>
				</tr>
  		</table>
	  </section>
		<para>
		  The response contains a JSON or XML encoded description of the data item.
	  </para>
		<xi:include href='samples/get_3_categories_DEFRA_transport_fuel_methodology_items_UID;values.xml' />
	</section>
</section>